Guide to the B. Noah Tilghman Color Transparencies and Other Materials Documenting Antarctica
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
B. Noah Tilghman color transparencies and other materials documenting Antarctica
1972-1974
SC1056
Tilghman, B. Noah
1.5 Linear feet and 2.19 gigabytes
The materials consist of approximately 1000 color transparencies taken by B. Noah Tilghman documenting various United States and New Zealand resaerch bases in Antarctica, including the construction of Siple Station, as well as general living conditions, individuals, and landscapes.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use.
Biographical/Historical note
The Siple experiment was a Stanford, NSF funded, VLF- triggered emission experiment that took place from 1973 to 1988. Siple Station was established to perform experiments that actively probed the magnetosphere using very low frequency (VLF) waves. The Station included a 21.2 km dipole antenna located in Antarctica at 75.93 S, 84.25 W. Its location was selected because of various characteristics:
1. The 2 km thick ice sheet at Siple allowed the construction of an antenna with a relatively high efficiency. With a 100 kW source, the antenna could obtain radiated powers on the order of 1 kW, which was necessary for stimulating wave-particle interactions in the magnetosphere.
2. Siple's magnetic conjugate point was easily accessible, near the city of Roberval (also in Lake Mistassini), Quebec.
3. Siple, at L = 4.3, was close to the plasmapause, where wave-particle resonances were likely to occur at the transmitted frequencies.
4. Siple could be operated year-round [1].
5. The station was effectively isolated from major EM noise in the VLF spectrum.
The objective of the Siple transmitter was to produce various formats, which allowed for controlled experiments to answer specific questions regarding triggered emissions. The observed data after transmission included many unexplained phenomena. Some of the more obvious phenomena includes (but definitely not limited to): rising and falling emissions, wave growth, entrainment, and multiple-hop echos.
Between 1973 and 1978, Siple operated with a transmitter known as Zeus. The Zeus transmitter could operate at one frequency at a time at powers up to 100kW. In 1978, the transmitter was replaced by the Jupiter transmitter, which could operate at multiple frequencies simultaneously and 150kW. In 1986, a second dipole antenna was added to explore polarization effects [2]. The Siple experiment ceased operation after the Antarctic summer of 1988.
Two receiving stations were operated during the Siple experiment. The first was located at Roberval, Quebec. The gradual northwesterly drift of Siple's conjugate point due to the secular variation of the geomagnetic field and the increasing interference from local power lines required the movement of the receiver to Lake Mistissini, Quebec during the later years of operation.
References
1.R. A. Helliwell and J. P. Katsufrakis, Upper Atmosphere Research in Antarctica, Chapter 5, Controlled Wave-Particle Interaction Experiments, pp. 100-129, Number 29 in the Antarctic Research Series. American Geophysical Union, 1978.
2. R. A. Helliwell, "Vlf wave stimulation experiments in the magnetosphere from Siple Station, Antarctica," Review of Geophysics, vol. 26, no. 3, pp. 551-578, August 1988.
Scope and Contents
The materials consist of approximately 1000 color slide transparencies taken by B. Noah Tilghman documenting various United States and New Zealand research bases in Antarctica, including the construction of Siple Station, as well as general living conditions, individuals, and landscapes.
Each slide has a unique code, which matches a photo log (photocopy) included in the collection. As each roll of film was being mailed for development, each roll was numbered. This is the last number in the slide code. Austral summer 1972-1973 was designated "Ant", while the 1973-1974 season is represented by the "K" in the center of the code. Each frame of the roll was numbered at the beginning of the notation.
The photo log gives photographic information as well as date, location and subject. Some of this information has also been written onto the individual slide frames. Abbreviations used include "EE" (electric eye) and "MPF" (maximum polarizing filter).
Access Terms
Helliwell, Robert A., 1920-2011.; Katsufrakis, John; Stanford University. STAR Lab.; Tilghman, B. Noah; United States Antarctic Research Program.; Antarctica; Color transparencies; Electromagnetism; Research--California--Stanford University.; Scientific research
Collection Contents
- Images
  - Color Transparencies (35mm)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - Other (Box 1)
  - Digital Surrogates
    - 1972_1973_Antarctica, 141 computer file(s) (JPG)
    - 1973_1974_Antarctica, 70 computer file(s) (JPG)
    - Misc Mix of Antarctica, 59 computer file(s) (JPG)
    - Photograph log, 1 computer file(s) (PDF)
  - Photos (prints), 1973 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Photo log book, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Records
  - Antarctica: A New Look (Box 2)
  - Antenna notes (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Arrival, processing, and departure procedures (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Communiques (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Corresondence, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Corresondence, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Corresondence re: Antarctica Service Medal, 1973-2003 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Departure, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Passage authorization, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Personnel manual, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Survival in Antarctica (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Thanksgiving day menu (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - U.S. Antarctic Research Program, orientation session, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - U.S. Antarctic Research Program sticker (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - "Your Stay at McMurdo Station Antarctica", 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 15)